OK.
Excellent so far we learned about the simple linear regression we predicted the dependent variable y
with a single regress or x.
It is time to level up now now we said that in real life a person's income does not depend solely on
education but also on their experience the time they spend with their current employer and so on.
House prices do not depend solely on their size but also on location and year of construction college
GPA cannot be predicted solely by students as a score but also by their high school GPA income gender
and so on.
If we want to make good models we need multiple regressions multiple regressions address the higher
complexity of problems the more variables you have the more factors you are considering.
In a model in the real world things depend on two three or even 10 or 20 factors.
All right so this is a population multiple regression model.
It is similar to a simple regression.
The main difference is there are a bunch of independent variables not just one what we are interested
in is the multiple regression equation.
We want to plug in numbers and predict outcomes right.
Once again why that is the inferred value and B zero is the int..
The independent variables range from X1 to x K B one to B.
K are there corresponding coefficients.
The last thing to say about multiple regressions is that it's not about the best fitting line any more.
Actually it stops being two dimensional and when we have over three dimensions there is no visual way
to represent the data.
So if it is not about the line what is it about.
It's about the best fitting model.
As we saw from the O LS What we really want is the least sum of squared errors All right so how do we
decrease the models error.
Well by increasing the explanatory power of the model SSD and SSI are like communicating vessels remember
each time we lower one.
The other goes higher with each additional variable.
We increase the explanatory power by zero or more than zero.
We can not lower it.
More variables usually equal a better fitting model in the next lesson we will see how to determine
the optimal number of variables to use.
Thanks for watching.