Remember when we talked about R-squared and I told you it was a very widely used measure of explanatory
power.
Well that was almost true.
We'll have to refine this measure its new version will be called the adjusted R-squared.
A statistician would always take a look at it when performing regression analysis.
So what does it adjust for.
Let's consider two statements we saw in the previous lessons.
One the R squared measures how much of the total variability is explained by our model and to multiple
regressions are always better than simple ones as with each additional variable that you add the explanatory
power may only increase or stay the same.
Considering the number of variables the adjusted R-squared is always smaller than the R-squared as it
penalizes excessive use of variables.
Let's create our first multiple regression to explain this point.
I'll import all the relevant libraries once again this time though.
I'll load the data from the file 1.0 to multiple linear regression dot CSP.
That's the file relevant for this lecture and you can download it from the Course resources as you can
see.
We have the same data with one additional variable called random 1 2 3.
I've generated a variable that assigns 1 2 or 3 randomly to each student.
We are 100 percent sure that this variable cannot predict college GPA.
So this is our new model college GPA is equal to be zero plus be 1 times S.A.T. score plus b 2 times
the random variable.
Here are the descriptive statistics.
What about the regression.
Why is still G.P.A. this time though we have two explanatory variables S.A.T. and random one to three
what we can do is declare x 1 as a data frame containing both series.
Great.
The rest remains unchanged.
Let's run the code and check out the newly created regression tables.
You can see the old ones in the box on the right.
We notice that the new R-Squared is zero point for 0 7 so it seems as we have increased the explanatory
power of the model but that our enthusiasm is dampened by the adjusted R-squared of 0.3 9:2 we were
penalized for adding an additional variable that had no strong explanatory power.
We have added information but have lost value.
Point is you should cherry pick your data as to exclude useless information however one would assume
regression analysis is smarter than that.
Right.
Adding an impractical variable should be pointed out by the model in some way.
Well that's true.
Look at the coefficient table we have determined the coefficient for the random 1 to 3 variable but
its p value is 0.7 6 to remember the null hypothesis of the test.
Beta 2 equals zero.
We cannot reject the null hypothesis that the 76 percent significance level.
This is an incredibly high p value.
Let me remind you that for a coefficient to be statistically significant We want a p value of less than
zero point zero five.
Our conclusion is that the variable random one to three not only worsens the explanatory power of the
model reflected by a lower adjusted r squared but is also insignificant.
Therefore it should be dropped altogether dropping useless variables is important.
You can see the original model changed from y hat.
Equals zero point 2 7 5 plus zero point zero zero 1 7 times x 1 2 y hat equals zero point 2 9 6 plus
zero point zero zero 1 7 times x 1.
Minus 0.00 a three times x 2.
The choice of third variable affected the intercept.
Whenever you have one variable that is ruining the model.
You should not use this model altogether because the bias of this variable is reflected into the coefficients
of the other variables.
The correct approach is to remove it from the aggression and run a new one.
Omitting the problematic predicter there is one more consideration concerning the removal of variables
from a model.
We can add 100 different variables to a model and probably the predictive power of the model will be
outstanding.
However this strategy makes regression analysis futile.
You are trying to use a few of independent variables that approximately predict the results.
The tradeoff is complex but simplicity is better rewarded than higher explanatory power.
Finally the adjusted R-squared is the basis for comparing regression models.
Once again it only makes sense to compare two models considering the same dependent variable and using
the same data set.
If we compare two models that are about two different dependent variables we will be making an apples
to oranges comparison.
If we use different data sets it is an apples to dinosaur's problem.
As you can see adjusted R-squared is a step in the right direction but should not be the only measure
trusted.
Caution is advised.
Whereas thorough logic and diligence are mandatory in our next lesson.
We will learn how to assess the overall significance of a model.
Thanks for watching.